<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--

    DO NOT ALTER OR REMOVE COPYRIGHT NOTICES OR THIS HEADER.

    Copyright (c) 2010-2012 Oracle and/or its affiliates. All rights reserved.

    The contents of this file are subject to the terms of either the GNU
    General Public License Version 2 only ("GPL") or the Common Development
    and Distribution License("CDDL") (collectively, the "License").  You
    may not use this file except in compliance with the License.  You can
    obtain a copy of the License at
    http://glassfish.java.net/public/CDDL+GPL_1_1.html
    or packager/legal/LICENSE.txt.  See the License for the specific
    language governing permissions and limitations under the License.

    When distributing the software, include this License Header Notice in each
    file and include the License file at packager/legal/LICENSE.txt.

    GPL Classpath Exception:
    Oracle designates this particular file as subject to the "Classpath"
    exception as provided by Oracle in the GPL Version 2 section of the License
    file that accompanied this code.

    Modifications:
    If applicable, add the following below the License Header, with the fields
    enclosed by brackets [] replaced by your own identifying information:
    "Portions Copyright [year] [name of copyright owner]"

    Contributor(s):
    If you wish your version of this file to be governed by only the CDDL or
    only the GPL Version 2, indicate your decision by adding "[Contributor]
    elects to include this software in this distribution under the [CDDL or GPL
    Version 2] license."  If you don't indicate a single choice of license, a
    recipient has the option to distribute your version of this file under
    either the CDDL, the GPL Version 2 or to extend the choice of license to
    its licensees as provided above.  However, if you add GPL Version 2 code
    and therefore, elected the GPL Version 2 license, then the option applies
    only if the new code is made subject to such option by the copyright
    holder.

-->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                 "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"[
<!ENTITY % ents SYSTEM "jersey.ent" >
%ents;
]>

<chapter id="client">
  <title>Client API</title>
    <para>This section introduces the JAX-RS Client API, which is a high-level Java based API for interoperating with RESTful Web services.
    It makes it very easy to interoperate with RESTful Web services and
    enables a developer to concisely and efficiently implement a reusable client-side solution that leverages existing and well established client-side HTTP implementations.
    </para>
    <para>The client API can be utilized to interoperate with any RESTful Web service, implemented using one of many frameworks, and is not restricted to services implemented using JAX-RS. However, developers familiar with JAX-RS should find the client API complementary to their services, especially if the client API is utilized by those services themselves, or to test those services.
    </para>
    <para>The goals of the client API are threefold:</para>
    <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Encapsulate a key constraint of the REST architectural style, namely the Uniform Interface Constraint and associated data elements, as client-side Java artifacts;
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Make it as easy to interoperate with RESTful Web services as the JAX-RS server-side API makes it easy to build RESTful Web services; and
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Share common concepts of the JAX-RS API between the server and the client side.
            </para>
        </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>The Client API supports a pluggable architecture to enable the use of different underlying HTTP client implementations. Several such implementations are supported by Jersey. To name a few we have a client connectors for <literal>Http(s)URLConnection</literal> classes
    supplied with the JDK; and the Grizzly client.
    </para>

    TODO: REWRITE THE FOLLOWING SECTIONS TO THE NEW JAX-RS 2.0 API
    <!--__________________________________________________________________________-->
    <section>
        <title>Uniform Interface Constraint</title>
        <para>The uniform interface constraint bounds the architecture of RESTful Web services so that a client, such
        as a browser, can utilize the same interface to communicate with any service. This is a very powerful concept
        in software engineering that makes Web-based search engines and service mash-ups possible. It induces properties
        such as:
        </para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>simplicity, the architecture is easier to understand and maintain; and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>modifiability or loose coupling, clients and services can evolve over time perhaps in new and
                unexpected ways, while retaining backwards compatibility.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>Further constraints are required:</para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>every resource is identified by a URI;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>a client interacts with the resource via HTTP requests and responses using a fixed set of
                HTTP methods;
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>one or more representations can be retured and are identified by media types; and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>the contents of which can link to further resources.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>The above process repeated over and again should be familiar to anyone who has used a browser to fill
        in HTML forms and follow links. That same process is applicable to non-browser based clients.
        </para>
        <para>Many existing Java-based client APIs, such as the Apache HTTP client API or
            <literal>java.net.HttpURLConnection</literal>
        supplied with the JDK place too much focus on the Client-Server constraint for the exchanges of request and
        responses rather than a resource, identified by a URI, and the use of a fixed set of HTTP methods.
        </para>
        <para>A resource in the Jersey client API is an instance of the Java class
            <ulink url="http://jersey.java.net/nonav/apidocs/&version;/jersey/com/sun/jersey/api/client/WebResource.html">WebResource</ulink>,
            and encapsulates a URI. The fixed set of HTTP methods are methods on
            <literal>WebResource</literal>
            or if using the builder
            pattern (more on this later) are the last methods to be called when invoking an HTTP method on a resource.
            The representations are Java types, instances of which, may contain links that new instances of
            <literal>WebResource</literal> may be created from.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Ease of use and reusing JAX-RS artifacts</title>
        <para>Since a resource is represented as a Java type it makes it easy to configure, pass around and inject in
        ways that is not so intuitive or possible with other client-side APIs.
        </para>
        <para>The Jersey Client API reuses many aspects of the JAX-RS and the Jersey implementation such as:</para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>URI building using
                    <ulink url="&jsr311.javadoc.path;/core/UriBuilder.html">UriBuilder</ulink> and
                    <ulink url="http://jersey.java.net/nonav/apidocs/&version;/jersey/com/sun/jersey/api/uri/UriTemplate.html">UriTemplate</ulink>
                    to safely build URIs;
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Support for Java types of representations such as
                    <literal>byte[]</literal>,
                    <literal>String</literal>,
                    <literal>InputStream</literal>,
                    <literal>File</literal>,
                    <literal>DataSource</literal>
                and JAXB beans in addition to Jersey specific features such as
                    <ulink url="http://jersey.java.net/nonav/apidocs/&version;/jersey/com/sun/jersey/api/json/package-summary.html">JSON</ulink> support and
                    <ulink url="http://jersey.java.net/nonav/apidocs/&version;/contribs/jersey-multipart/index.html">MIME Multipart</ulink> support.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Using the builder pattern to make it easier to construct requests.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>Some APIs, like the Apache HTTP client or
            <ulink url="http://docs.oracle.com/javase/1.5.0/docs/api/java/net/HttpURLConnection.html">java.net.HttpURLConnection</ulink>,
            can be rather hard to use and/or require too much code to do something relatively simple.
        </para>
        <para>This is why the Jersey Client API provides support for wrapping HttpURLConnection and the Apache
        HTTP client. Thus it is possible to get the benefits of the established implementations and features
        while getting the ease of use benefit.
        </para>
        <para>It is not intuitive to send a POST request with form parameters and receive a response as a
        JAXB object with such an API. For example with the Jersey API this is very easy:
        <example>
            <title>POST request with form parameters</title>
            <programlisting language="java" linenumbering="numbered">Form f = new Form();
f.add(&quot;x&quot;, &quot;foo&quot;);
f.add(&quot;y&quot;, &quot;bar&quot;);

Client c = Client.create();
WebResource r = c.resource(&quot;http://localhost:8080/form&quot;);

JAXBBean bean = r.
    type(MediaType.APPLICATION_FORM_URLENCODED_TYPE)
    .accept(MediaType.APPLICATION_JSON_TYPE)
    .post(JAXBBean.class, f);</programlisting>
        </example>
        In the above code a
            <ulink url="http://jersey.java.net/nonav/apidocs/&version;/jersey/com/sun/jersey/api/representation/Form.html">Form</ulink> is created with two parameters, a new
            <ulink url="http://jersey.java.net/nonav/apidocs/&version;/jersey/com/sun/jersey/api/client/WebResource.html">WebResource</ulink> instance is created from a
            <ulink url="http://jersey.java.net/nonav/apidocs/&version;/jersey/com/sun/jersey/api/client/Client.html">Client</ulink> then the
            <literal>Form</literal> instance is <literal>POST</literal>ed to
            the resource, identified with the form media type, and the response is requested as an instance of a JAXB bean
            with an acceptable media type identifying the Java Script Object
            Notation (JSON) format. The Jersey client API manages the serialization of the <literal>Form</literal> instance to produce the
            request and de-serialization of the response to consume as an instance of a JAXB bean.
        </para>
        <para>If the code above was written using
            <literal>HttpURLConnection</literal> then the developer would have to write code to serialize the
        form sent in the POST request and de-serialize the response to the JAXB bean. In addition further code would have to be written
        to make it easy to reuse the same resource “http://localhost:8080/form” that is encapsulated in the
            <literal>WebResource</literal> type.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Getting started with the Jersey client</title>
        <para>Refer to the
         <ulink url="http://jersey.java.net/nonav/documentation/&version;/chapter_deps.html#chapter_deps">dependencies chapter</ulink>,
            and specifically the <ulink url="http://jersey.java.net/nonav/documentation/&version;/chapter_deps.html#core_client">Core client</ulink> section,
            for details on the dependencies when using the Jersey client with Maven and Ant.
        </para>
        <para>Refer to the
            <ulink url="http://jersey.java.net/nonav/apidocs/&version;/jersey/com/sun/jersey/api/client/package-summary.html">Java API documentation</ulink> for details on the Jersey client API packages and classes.
        </para>
        <para>Refer to the
            <ulink url="http://jersey.java.net/nonav/apidocs/&version;/contribs/jersey-apache-client/index.html">Java API Apache HTTP client documentation</ulink> for details on how to use the Jersey client API with the Apache HTTP client.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Overview of the API</title>
        <para>To utilize the client API it is first necessary to create an instance of a
            <ulink url="http://jersey.java.net/nonav/apidocs/&version;/jersey/com/sun/jersey/api/client/Client.html">Client</ulink>, for example:
            <programlisting language="java">    Client c = Client.create();</programlisting>
        </para>
        <section>
            <title>Configuring a Client and WebResource</title>
            <para>The client instance can then be configured by setting properties on the map returned from
            the
                <literal>getProperties</literal> methods or by calling the specific setter methods,
            for example the following configures the client to perform automatic redirection for
            appropriate responses:
                <programlisting language="java">    c.getProperties().put(
        ClientConfig.PROPERTY_FOLLOW_REDIRECTS, true);</programlisting>
            which is equivalent to the following:
                <programlisting language="java">    c.setFollowRedirects(true);</programlisting>
            Alternatively it is possible to create a <literal>Client</literal> instance using a
                <ulink url="http://jersey.java.net/nonav/apidocs/&version;/jersey/com/sun/jersey/api/client/config/ClientConfig.html">ClientConfig</ulink>
            object for example:
                <programlisting language="java">    ClientConfig cc = new DefaultClientConfig();
    cc.getProperties().put(
        ClientConfig.PROPERTY_FOLLOW_REDIRECTS, true);
    Client c = Client.create(cc);</programlisting>
            </para>
            <para>Once a client instance is created and configured it is then possible to obtain a
                <ulink url="http://jersey.java.net/nonav/apidocs/&version;/jersey/com/sun/jersey/api/client/WebResource.html">WebResource</ulink>
                instance, which will inherit the configuration declared on the client instance.
                For example, the following creates a reference to a Web resource with the URI
                “http://localhost:8080/xyz”:
                <programlisting language="java">    WebResource r = c.resource(&quot;http://localhost:8080/xyz&quot;);</programlisting>
            and redirection will be configured for responses to requests invoked on the Web resource.
            </para>
            <para>
                <literal>Client</literal> instances are expensive resources. It is recommended a configured
            instance is reused for the creation of Web resources. The creation of Web resources, the building
            of requests and receiving of responses are guaranteed to be thread safe. Thus a
                <literal>Client</literal>
            instance and
                <literal>WebResource</literal> instances may be shared between multiple threads.
            </para>
            <para>In the above cases a
                <literal>WebResource</literal> instance will utilize
                <literal>HttpUrlConnection</literal> or
                <literal>HttpsUrlConnection</literal>,
            if the URI scheme of the
                <literal>WebResource</literal> is “http” or “https” respectively.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Building a request</title>
            <para>Requests to a Web resource are built using the builder pattern (see
                <ulink url="http://jersey.java.net/nonav/apidocs/&version;/jersey/com/sun/jersey/api/client/RequestBuilder.html">RequestBuilder</ulink>)
                where the terminating method corresponds to an HTTP method (see
                <ulink url="http://jersey.java.net/nonav/apidocs/&version;/jersey/com/sun/jersey/api/client/UniformInterface.html">UniformInterface</ulink>).
                For example,
                <programlisting language="java">    String response = r.accept(
        MediaType.APPLICATION_JSON_TYPE,
        MediaType.APPLICATION_XML_TYPE).
        header(&quot;X-FOO&quot;, &quot;BAR&quot;).
        get(String.class);</programlisting>
            </para>
            <para>The above sends a GET request with an
                <literal>Accept</literal> header of
                <literal>application/json</literal>,
                <literal>application/xml</literal> and a
            non-standard header
                <literal>X-FOO</literal> of
                <literal>BAR</literal>.
            </para>
            <para>If the request has a request entity (or representation) then an instance
            of a Java type can be declared in the terminating HTTP method, for
                <literal>PUT</literal>,
                <literal>POST</literal> and
                <literal>DELETE</literal> requests.
            For example, the following sends a POST request:
                <programlisting language="java">    String request = &quot;content&quot;;
    String response = r.accept(
        MediaType.APPLICATION_JSON_TYPE,
        MediaType.APPLICATION_XML_TYPE).
        header(&quot;X-FOO&quot;, &quot;BAR&quot;).
        post(String.class, request);</programlisting>
            where the String &quot;content&quot; will be serialized as the request
            entity (see the section &quot;Java instances and types for representations&quot;
            section for further details on the supported Java types). The
            <literal>Content-Type</literal> of the request entity may be declared
            using the <literal>type</literal> builder method as follows:
            <programlisting language="java">    String response = r.accept(
         MediaType.APPLICATION_JSON_TYPE,
         MediaType.APPLICATION_XML_TYPE).
         header(&quot;X-FOO&quot;, &quot;BAR&quot;).
         type(MediaType.TEXT_PLAIN_TYPE).
         post(String.class, request);</programlisting>
            or alternatively the request entity and type may be declared
            using the entity method as follows:
            <programlisting language="java">    String response = r.accept(
         MediaType.APPLICATION_JSON_TYPE,
         MediaType.APPLICATION_XML_TYPE).
         header(&quot;X-FOO&quot;, &quot;BAR&quot;).
         entity(request, MediaType.TEXT_PLAIN_TYPE).
         post(String.class);</programlisting>
            </para>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>Receiving a response</title>
                <para>If the response has a entity (or representation) then the
                Java type of the instance required is declared in the terminating HTTP method.
                In the above examples a response entity is expected and an instance of <literal>String</literal>
                is requested. The response entity will be de-serialized to a String
                instance.</para>
                <para>If response meta-data is required then the Java type
                    <ulink url="http://jersey.java.net/nonav/apidocs/&version;/jersey/com/sun/jersey/api/client/ClientResponse.html">ClientResponse</ulink>
                    can be declared from which the response status, headers and entity may be obtained.
                    For example, the following gets both the entity tag and response entity from the
                    response:
                <programlisting language="java">    ClientResponse response = r.get(ClientResponse.class);
    EntityTag e = response.getEntityTag();
    String entity = response.getEntity(String.class);</programlisting></para>
                <para>If the <literal>ClientResponse</literal> type is not utilized and the response
                status is greater than or equal to 300 then the runtime exception
                 <ulink url="http://jersey.java.net/nonav/apidocs/&version;/jersey/com/sun/jersey/api/client/UniformInterfaceException.html">UniformInterfaceException</ulink>
                 is thrown. This exception may be caught and the <literal>ClientResponse</literal> obtained as follows:
                <programlisting language="java">    try {
        String entity = r.get(String.class);
    } catch (UniformInterfaceException ue) {
        ClientResponse response = ue.getResponse();
    }</programlisting></para>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>Creating new WebResources from a WebResource</title>
                <para>A new
                    <ulink url="http://jersey.java.net/nonav/apidocs/&version;/jersey/com/sun/jersey/api/client/WebResource.html">WebResource</ulink>
                    can be created from an existing <literal>WebResource</literal> by building from the latter's URI.
                    Thus it is possible to build the request URI before building the request. For example, the
                    following appends a new path segment and adds some query parameters:
                <programlisting language="java">    WebResource r = c.resource(&quot;http://localhost:8080/xyz&quot;);

    MultivaluedMap&lt;String, String&gt; params = MultivaluedMapImpl();
    params.add(&quot;foo&quot;, &quot;x&quot;);
    params.add(&quot;bar&quot;, &quot;y&quot;);

    String response = r.path(&quot;abc&quot;).
        queryParams(params).
        get(String.class);</programlisting>
                that results in a GET request to the URI &quot;http://localhost:8080/xyz/abc?foo=x&amp;bar=y&quot;.</para>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>Java instances and types for representations</title>
                <para>All the Java types for representations supported by the Jersey server side for
                requests and responses are also supported on the client side. This includes the standard
                Java types as specified by JAX-RS in
                    <ulink url="http://jsr311.java.net/nonav/releases/1.0/spec/index.html">section 4.2.4</ulink>
                    in addition to JSON, Atom and Multipart MIME as supported by Jersey.
                </para>
                <para>To process a response entity (or representation) as a stream of bytes use InputStream as follows:
                <programlisting language="java">    InputStream in = r.get(InputStream.class);
    // Read from the stream
    in.close();</programlisting>
                Note that it is important to close the stream after processing so that resources are freed up.</para>
                <para>To <literal>POST</literal> a file use <literal>File</literal> as follows:
                <programlisting language="java">    File f = ...
    String response = r.post(String.class, f);</programlisting>
                Refer to the
                    <ulink url="https://maven.java.net/service/local/artifact/maven/redirect?r=&repository;&amp;g=com.sun.jersey.samples&amp;a=jaxb&amp;v=&version;&amp;c=project&amp;e=zip">JAXB sample</ulink> to see how JAXB with XML and JSON can be utilized with the client API (more specifically, see the unit tests).
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Adding support for new representations</title>
            <para>The support for new application-defined representations as Java types requires the
            implementation of the same provider-based interfaces as for the server side JAX-RS API, namely
                <ulink url="http://jsr311.java.net/nonav/javadoc/javax/ws/rs/ext/MessageBodyReader.html">MessageBodyReader</ulink> and
                <ulink url="http://jsr311.java.net/nonav/javadoc/javax/ws/rs/ext/MessageBodyWriter.html">MessageBodyWriter</ulink>,
                respectively, for request and response entities (or inbound and outbound representations). Refer to the
                <ulink url="https://maven.java.net/service/local/artifact/maven/redirect?r=&repository;&amp;g=com.sun.jersey.samples&amp;a=entity-provider&amp;v=&version;&amp;c=project&amp;e=zip">entity provider</ulink>
                sample for such implementations utilized on the server side.
            </para>
            <para>Classes or implementations of the provider-based interfaces need to be registered with a
            <literal>ClientConfig</literal> and passed to the <literal>Client</literal> for creation. The following
            registers a provider class <literal>MyReader</literal> which will be instantiated by Jersey:
            <programlisting language="java">    ClientConfig cc = new DefaultClientConfig();
    cc.getClasses().add(MyReader.class);
    Client c = Client.create(cc);</programlisting>
            The following registers an instance or singleton of MyReader:
            <programlisting language="java">    ClientConfig cc = new DefaultClientConfig();
    MyReader reader = ...
    cc.getSingletons().add(reader);
    Client c = Client.create(cc);</programlisting></para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Using filters</title>
            <para>Filtering requests and responses can provide useful functionality that is hidden from the
            application layer of building and sending requests, and processing responses. Filters can
            read/modify the request URI, headers and entity or read/modify the response status,
            headers and entity.</para>
            <para>
            The <literal>Client</literal> and <literal>WebResource</literal> classes extend from
            <ulink url="http://jersey.java.net/nonav/apidocs/&version;/jersey/com/sun/jersey/api/client/filter/Filterable.html">Filterable</ulink>
            and that enables the addition of
            <ulink url="http://jersey.java.net/nonav/apidocs/&version;/jersey/com/sun/jersey/api/client/filter/ClientFilter.html">ClientFilter</ulink>
            instances. A <literal>WebResource</literal> will inherit filters from its creator, which
            can be a <literal>Client</literal> or another <literal>WebResource</literal>.
            Additional filters can be added to a <literal>WebResource</literal> after it has been
            created. For requests, filters are applied
            in reverse order, starting with the <literal>WebResource</literal> filters and then
            moving to the inherited filters.
            For responses, filters are applied in order, starting with inherited filters
            and followed by the filters added to the <literal>WebResource</literal>. All filters
            are applied in the order in which they were added.
            For instance, in the following example the <literal>Client</literal> has two filters added,
            <literal>filter1</literal> and <literal>filter2</literal>, in that order, and the
            <literal>WebResource</literal> has one filter added, <literal>filter3</literal>:
            <programlisting language="java">    ClientFilter filter1 = ...
    ClientFilter filter2 = ...
    Client c = Client.create();
    c.addFilter(filter1);
    c.addFilter(filter2);

    ClientFilter filter3 = ...
    WebResource r = c.resource(...);
    r.addFilter(filter3);</programlisting>
            After a request has been built the request is filtered by <literal>filter3</literal>,
            <literal>filter2</literal> and <literal>filter1</literal> in that order. After the response
            has been received the response is filtered by <literal>filter1</literal>,
            <literal>filter2</literal> and <literal>filter3</literal> in that order, before the
            response is returned.</para>
            <para>Filters are implemented using the “russian doll” stack-based pattern where a
            filter is responsible for calling the next filter in the ordered list of filters
            (or the next filter in the “chain” of filters).
            The basic template for a filter is as follows:
            <programlisting language="java">    class AppClientFilter extends ClientFilter {
        public ClientResponse handle(ClientRequest cr) {
            // Modify the request
            ClientRequest mcr = modifyRequest(cr);
            // Call the next filter
            ClientResponse resp = getNext().handle(mcr);
            // Modify the response
            return modifyResponse(resp);
        }
    }</programlisting></para>
            <para>The filter modifies the request (if required) by creating a new
            <ulink url="http://jersey.java.net/nonav/apidocs/&version;/jersey/com/sun/jersey/api/client/ClientRequest.html">ClientRequest</ulink>
            or modifying the state of the passed <literal>ClientRequest</literal> before calling the
            next filter. The call to the next request will return
            the response, a <literal>ClientResponse</literal>. The filter
            modifies the response (if required) by creating a new <literal>ClientResponse</literal>
            or modifying the state of the returned <literal>ClientResponse</literal>.
            Then the filter returns the modified response.
            Filters are re-entrant and may be called by multiple threads performing requests
            and processing responses.</para>
            <section>
                <title>Supported filters</title>
                <para>The Jersey Client API currently supports two filters:</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>A GZIP content encoding filter,
                            <ulink url="http://jersey.java.net/nonav/apidocs/&version;/jersey/com/sun/jersey/api/client/filter/GZIPContentEncodingFilter.html">GZIPContentEncodingFilter</ulink>.
                            If this filter is added then a request entity is compressed with the
                            <literal>Content-Encoding</literal>
                            of <literal>gzip</literal>, and a response entity if compressed with a
                            <literal>Content-Encoding</literal> of <literal>gzip</literal> is
                            decompressed. The filter declares an <literal>Accept-Encoding</literal>
                            of <literal>gzip</literal>.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>A logging filter,
                            <ulink url="http://jersey.java.net/nonav/apidocs/&version;/jersey/com/sun/jersey/api/client/filter/LoggingFilter.html">LoggingFilter</ulink>.
                            If this filter is added then the request and response headers as well as the entities are logged
                            to a declared output stream if present, or to <literal>System.out</literal> if not.
                            Often this filter will be placed at the end of the ordered list of
                            filters to log the request before it is sent
                            and the response after it is received.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
                <para>The filters above are good examples that show how to modify or read
                request and response entities. Refer to the
                    <ulink url="https://maven.java.net/service/local/artifact/maven/redirect?r=&repository;&amp;g=com.sun.jersey&amp;a=jersey-client&amp;v=&version;&amp;e=jar">source code</ulink>
                    of the Jersey client for more details.
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Testing services</title>
            <para>The Jersey client API was originally developed to aid the testing of the Jersey server-side,
            primarily to make it easier to write functional tests in conjunction with the JUnit framework
            for execution and reporting. It is used extensively and there are currently over 1000 tests.</para>
            <para>Embedded servers, Grizzly and a special in-memory server, are utilized to deploy the
            test-based services. Many of the Jersey samples contain tests that utilize the client API to
            server both for testing and examples of how to use the API. The samples utilize Grizzly or
            embedded Glassfish to deploy the services.</para>
            <para>The following code snippets are presented from the single unit test
            <literal>HelloWorldWebAppTest</literal> of the
                <ulink url="https://maven.java.net/service/local/artifact/maven/redirect?r=&repository;&amp;g=com.sun.jersey.samples&amp;a=helloworld-webapp&amp;v=&version;&amp;c=project&amp;e=zip">helloworld-webapp</ulink>
                sample.
            The <literal>setUp</literal> method, called before a test is executed, creates an instance of
            the Glassfish server, deploys the application, and a <literal>WebResource</literal> instance
            that references the base resource:
            <programlisting language="java">    @Override
    protected void setUp() throws Exception {
        super.setUp();

        // Start Glassfish
        glassfish = new GlassFish(BASE_URI.getPort());

        // Deploy Glassfish referencing the web.xml
        ScatteredWar war = new ScatteredWar(
            BASE_URI.getRawPath(), new File("src/main/webapp"),
            new File("src/main/webapp/WEB-INF/web.xml"),
            Collections.singleton(
                new File("target/classes").
                    toURI().toURL()));
        glassfish.deploy(war);

        Client c = Client.create();
        r = c.resource(BASE_URI);
    }</programlisting>
            The <literal>tearDown</literal> method, called after a test is executed,
            stops the Glassfish server.
            <programlisting language="java">    @Override
   protected void tearDown() throws Exception {
        super.tearDown();
        glassfish.stop();
   }</programlisting></para>
            <para>The <literal>testHelloWorld</literal> method tests that the response
            to a <literal>GET</literal> request to the Web resource returns “Hello World”:
            <programlisting language="java">    public void testHelloWorld() throws Exception {
       String responseMsg = r.path("helloworld").
           get(String.class);
       assertEquals("Hello World", responseMsg);
   }</programlisting>
            Note the use of the <literal>path</literal> method on the <literal>WebResource</literal> to
            build from the base <literal>WebResource</literal>.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Security with Http(s)URLConnection</title>
            <section>
            <title>With Http(s)URLConnection</title>
            <para>The support for security, specifically HTTP authentication and/or cookie management
            with <literal>Http(s)URLConnection</literal> is limited due to constraints in the API.
            There are currently no specific features or properties on the <literal>Client</literal> class that
            can be set to support HTTP authentication. However, since the client API, by default, utilizes
            <literal>HttpURLConnection</literal> or <literal>HttpsURLConnection</literal>,
            it is possible to configure system-wide
            security settings (which is obviously not sufficient for multiple client configurations).</para>
            <para>For HTTP authentication the <literal>java.net.Authenticator</literal> can
            be extended and statically registered. Refer to the
                <ulink url="http://docs.oracle.com/javase/6/docs/technotes/guides/net/http-auth.html">Http authentication</ulink>
                document for more details.
            For cookie management the <literal>java.net.CookieHandler</literal> can be extended
            and statically registered. Refer to the
                <ulink url="http://docs.oracle.com/javase/6/docs/technotes/guides/net/http-cookie.html">Cookie Management</ulink>
                document for more details.
            </para>
            <para>To utilize HTTP with SSL it is necessary to utilize the “https” scheme.
            For certificate-based authentication see the class
                <ulink url="http://jersey.java.net/nonav/apidocs/latest/jersey/com/sun/jersey/client/urlconnection/HTTPSProperties.html">HTTPSProperties</ulink>
                for how to set <literal>javax.net.ssl.HostnameVerifier</literal> and
                <literal>javax.net.ssl.SSLContext</literal>.
            </para>
            </section>
            <section>
            <title>With Apache HTTP client</title>
            <para>The support for HTTP authentication and cookies is much better with the Apache HTTP
            client than with <literal>HttpURLConnection</literal>.
            See the Java documentation for the package
                <ulink url="http://jersey.java.net/nonav/apidocs/&version;/contribs/jersey-apache-client/com/sun/jersey/client/apache/package-summary.html">com.sun.jersey.client.apache</ulink>,
                <ulink url="http://jersey.java.net/nonav/apidocs/&version;/contribs/jersey-apache-client/com/sun/jersey/client/apache/config/ApacheHttpClientState.html">ApacheHttpClientState</ulink> and
                <ulink url="http://jersey.java.net/nonav/apidocs/&version;/contribs/jersey-apache-client/com/sun/jersey/client/apache/config/ApacheHttpClientConfig.html">ApacheHttpClientConfig</ulink> for more details.
            </para>
            </section>
        </section>

</chapter>
